Dorothy C. Miller
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Edward Hicks Catalog, 1934-1984, Series 10:; (Boxes 20-22; 21.5 linear ft.)
  - Notes and Draft Preface, 1981-1983 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Paintings, circa 1935-circa 1981, (3 folders) (Box 21, Folder 12-14)
  - Page Proofs, circa 1983, (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 15-16)
  - Research Material, Photostats of Hicks Documentation, circa 1970s circa 1970s (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Research Postcards, circa 1970s (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Text Draft, circa 1980s (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Transcripts for "A Quaker's Colors: A Biography of Edward Hicks" by Robert W. Abendroth, circa 20th century (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Printed Material, 1938-1946 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Printed Material, 1951-1959 (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - Printed Material, 1960-1967, (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 23-24)
  - Printed Material, 1973-1978, (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 25-26)
  - Printed Material, 1980-1981 (Box 21, Folder 27)
  - Printed Material, Edward Hicks, Primitive Quaker. His Religion in Relation to His Art by Eleanore Price Mather, 1970 (Box 21, Folder 28)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalogs, 1941-1948 (Box 21, Folder 29)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalogs, 1953-1968 (Box 21, Folder 30)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalogs, 1970-1975 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalogs, 1980-1983 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork (Box 22)
    - Master Set 1: "Earliest Peaceable Kingdom, Peaceable Kingdom of the Branch" (Yale, Aarfal, Sussfi), circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Master Set 2: "Peaceable Kingdoms with Banners," 1827-1837, circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Master Set 3: "Transitional Peaceable Kingdoms," circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Master Set 4: "Seated Lions," Peaceable Kingdom, circa 1941 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Master Set 5: "Middle Kingdoms, Lions in Profile," Peaceable Kingdom, circa 1970s-1981 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Master Set 6: Peaceable Kingdom, circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Master Set 7: Peaceable Kingdom, circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Master Set 8: "Farms," circa 1942, circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Master Set 9: "Grave of William Penn and Penn's Treaty with Indians," circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Master Set 10: "Washington Crossing the Delaware," circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Master Set 11: Miscellaneous Subjects, circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Duplicates and Miscellaneous, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 14)
- General Research Files, 1930s-1980, Series 11:; (Boxes 22-23; 0.8 linear ft.)
  This series contains materials relating to Miller's research projects and interests, particularly focusing on early American art and American folk art. Found here is correspondence, some of which relates to her curatorial work at MOMA. There is correspondence with Ed Fuller regarding his work about sculptor William Edmondson and with Wanda Corn about her research on American folk art. Also found are notes and correspondence providing scattered documentation of the collecting activities of Holger Cahill, Edith Halpert, Miller and others during the 1930s-1940s, and on folk art exhibitions organized by Cahill, as well as printed material, such as news clippings and journal articles on the subject of American folk art.
  The bulk of the series is comprised of photographs of artwork.
  - American Folk Art (Box 22)
    - Correspondence and Notes, 1930s-1968, (2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 15-16)
    - Correspondence and Notes, 1970-1980 (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, Ed Fuller Manuscript on William Edmondson, 1971-1973 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Manuscript of Thesis by Wanda Corn, 1965 (Box 22, Folder 19)
    - Printed Material, 1935-1965, (2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 20-21)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Unknown and A, circa 1930s-circa 1970s, (4 folders) (Box 22, Folder 22-25)
  - Photographs of Artwork, B, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 26)
  - Photographs of Artwork, C-D circa 1930s-circa 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 27-28)
  - Photographs of Artwork, E-F, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 29)
  - Photographs of Artwork, G, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 30)
  - Photographs of Artwork, H circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of Artwork, I-K, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 32)
  - Photographs of Artwork, L-M, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 33)
  - Photographs of Artwork, N-Q circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 22, Folder 34)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Rivera, Diego, circa 1930s-circa 1970s, (2 slide boxes, rolled photos) (Box 22, Folder 35-36)
  - Photographs of Artwork, R-S, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Artwork, T, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork, U-Z circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 23, Folder 3)
- Exhibition Files, 1932-1986, Series 12:; (Box 23; 0.6 linear ft.)
  This series contains materials related to three exhibitions. A press release and a label is found for the landmark exhibition American Folk Art: The Art of the Common Man in America, organized by Holger Cahill for the Museum of Modern Art in 1932-1933. Also found here are two copies of the catalog and index cards of artwork for the First Municipal Art Exhibition (1934) organized by Miller and Cahill and shown at the Rockefeller Center in New York; one catalog is annotated with addresses of the artists. Additional scattered documents concern the galleries or Salons of America of the exhibition.
  One folder relates to the exhibition Dorothy C. Miller: With An Eye to American Art, held at the Smith College Museum of Art in 1985 that was inspired by Miller's famous series of "American" shows at MOMA.
  - American Folk Art: The Art of the Common Man in America (1932-1933: Museum of Modern Art), 1932-1933 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - First Municipal Art Exhibition (1934: New York), 1934 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - First Municipal Art Exhibition (1934: New York), Card Catalog A-J, 1934 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - First Municipal Art Exhibition (1934: New York), Card Catalog K-Z, 1934 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Salons of America (1934: New York), 1971 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Dorothy C. Miller: With An Eye To American Art (1985: Smith College Museum of Art), 1985-1986 (Box 23, Folder 9)
- Works of Art, circa 1924-circa 1982, Series 13:; (Boxes 23-25; 1.5 linear ft.)
  Original artwork consists primarily of a large collection of artists' greeting cards sent to Dorothy Miller and Holger Cahill. There are also a few scattered sketches and drawings. Artists include Elise Asher, Ilya Bolotowsky, Bernard Childs, Lew Davis, Jay DeFeo, Rene d' Harnoncourt, Lyonel Feininger, Pop Hart, Grace Hartigan, Bernard Karpel, Stanley Landsmen, William Littlefield, Agnes Sims and Hiram Williams.
  Artwork is arranged alphabetically by name of artist.
  - Original Christmas Cards (Box 23)
    - A, circa 1956-circa 1969, (2 folders; see also Box 25) (Box 23, Folder 10-11)
    - B, circa 1938-circa 1976, (3 folders) (Box 23, Folder 12-14)
    - Blumenthal, Ann and Joseph, 1937-1965, (2 folders) (Box 23, Folder 15-16)
    - C, circa 1938-circa 1982, (1 of 3 folders) (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - C, circa 1938-circa 1982, (2-3 of 3 folders) (Box 24, Folder 1-2)
    - D, circa 1941 circa 1972, (see also Box 25) (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - E, 1953, undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - F, 1946-1947, undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - G, circa 1955-circa 1964, (see also Box 25) (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - H, circa 1924-circa 1964 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - I, circa 1955-circa 1968 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - K, circa 1953-circa 1976, (3 folders; see also Box 25) (Box 24, Folder 9-11)
    - L, circa 1953-circa 1963, (see also Box 25) (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - M, circa 1953-circa 1978, (2 folders) (Box 24, Folder 13-14)
    - N-O, circa 1965-circa 1977 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - P, circa 1938-circa 1968, (see also Box 25) (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - R, circa 1956-circa 1971, (see also Box 25) (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - S, circa 1945-circa 1976, (3 folders; see also Box 25) (Box 24, Folder 18-20)
    - T, 1964-1967, undated (Box 24, Folder 21)
    - V, 1954-1965, (see also Box 25) (Box 24, Folder 22)
    - W, circa 1949-circa 1969 (Box 24, Folder 23)
    - Y-Z, circa 1957-circa 1977 (Box 24, Folder 24)
  - Spencer, Niles, Pencil Sketch of Sadakichi Hartmann, circa 1940s-circa 1950s (Box 24, Folder 25)
  - Unidentified Drawings, Watercolors, Prints, undated (Box 24, Folder 26)
  - Oversized Original Christmas Cards (Box 25 (sol))
    - Oversized A (Arpel; Asher, Elise), circa 1956-circa 1969, (From Box 23, F 10-11) (Box 25 (sol))
    - Oversized D (Davis, Lew) circa 1941-circa 1972, (From Box 24, F 3) (Box 25 (sol))
    - Oversized G (Gisiger, Jean-George), circa 1955-circa 1964, (From Box 24, F 6) (Box 25 (sol))
    - Oversized K (Karpel, Bernard; Kawashima, T.), circa 1953-circa 1976, (From Box 24, F 9-11) (Box 25 (sol))
    - Oversized L (Landsmen, Stanley; Littlefield, William), circa 1953-circa 1963, (From Box 24, F 12) (Box 25 (sol))
    - Oversized P (Pereira Irene Rice), circa 1938-circa 1968, (From Box 24, F 16) (Box 25 (sol))
    - Oversized R (Rowan), circa 1956-circa 1971, (From Box 24, F 17) (Box 25 (sol))
    - Oversized S (Sims, Agnes), circa 1945-circa 1976, (From Box 24, F 18-20) (Box 25 (sol))
    - Oversized V (Vasarely), 1954-1965, (From Box 24, F 22) (Box 25 (sol))
- Photographs, 1926-circa 1970s, Series 14:; (Boxes 24-25; 0.3 linear ft.)
  Photographs are of Dorothy Miller, including portraits by Soichi Sunami, and of Miller with others, including Bernard Pfriem. There are two prints and a series of 9 transparencies labeled as having been taken by artist Lyonel Feininger of Miller in the 1950s. There are also photographs of Holger Cahill and Curt Valentin. Also found are transparencies of a portrait of Holger Cahill by Icelandic artist Nina Tryggvadottir.
  - Photographs of Miller, Passport Photos, circa 1930s, 1959 (Box 24, Folder 27)
  - Photographs of Miller, Portraits, 1930s, (see also Box 25) (Box 24, Folder 28)
  - Photographs of Miller and Others, circa 1950s (Box 24, Folder 29)
  - Transparencies of Miller and Others, circa 1950s (Box 24, Folder 30)
  - Photographs of Miller and Others, Newark Art Museum Apprentice Class, 1926 (Box 24, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of Miller and Others, Smith College Commencement, 1959 (Box 24, Folder 32)
  - Photographs of Others, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 24, Folder 33)
  - Photographs, Miscellaneous, 1938 (Box 24, Folder 34)
  - Transparencies of Artwork, circa 1950s (Box 24, Folder 35)
  - Oversized Photograph of Miller by Soichi Sunami, Portrait, circa 1932, (From Box 24, F 28) (Box 25 (sol))